Guide to the Rudolph John Anderson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Rudolph John Anderson papers
1917-1962
MS 37
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box, 1 folio)
Writings and memorabilia of Rudolph John Anderson, professor of chemistry at Yale University, 1927-1948. The papers contain autobiographical memoirs, essays on the history of chemistry by Anderson and drafts of his book, The Chemistry of Lipoids..., published in 1938.
Anderson, Rudolph J. (Rudolph John), 1879-1961
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Rudolph J. Anderson in 1968, and of the Yale University Chemistry Department in 1955.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Rudolph John Anderson was born in Haina, Sweden, on September 15, 1879. He was the son of Anders and Johanna Anderson, and came from a family of farmers. In 1893, at age fourteen, Anderson immigrated alone to the United States.
Anderson graduated from the Harvard Grammar School, Cambridge, Massachusetts, in 1897. He soon found it financially impossible to continue his education. At this time his ambition in life was to be a locomotive engineer. Anderson secured a job in a chemistry lab in New Orleans and soon acquired what was to be a life-long interest in chemistry. Gradually, over a period of twenty-two years, he earned college degrees, culminating in a Ph.D. in Chemistry from Cornell University in 1919. His education proceeded as follows:
*Degree of Graduate in Pharmacy, New Orleans College of Pharmacy, 1902
*B.S. From Tulane University, 1906
*Graduate work at Tulane, 1906-1907
*Attended Upsala University, Sweden, 1909-1910
*Studied at the University of Berlin, 1910-1911, and again in 1917
*Worked at University College, London, 1914-1915
*Ph.D. from Cornell University, 1919
In 1947, Anderson received an honorary degree from the University of Lund, Sweden. The degree was an honorary Doctorate of Medicine, awarded to him as Professor Emeritus of Yale University for his chemical research.
After teaching chemistry at Cornell for a number of years, Anderson left to join the faculty of Yale University. From 1927 to 1948, he was a Professor of Chemistry at Yale. He held the title of Professor Emeritus from 1948 until his death in 1961.
Rudolph Ander devoted his life to the study of chemical substances in plants, such as the chemical called phytin, and to the study of bacteria. His discoveries in the field of lipoids of tubercle bacilli were outstanding.
As well as contributing articles to the Journal of Biological Chemistry and to the Journal of American Chemistry, Anderson became increasingly involved in editing scientific work. He was on the editorial board of the Journal of Biological Chemistry from 1931 until 1958, and was managing editor from 1937 until 1958. The December 1958 edition of Biological Chemistry was dedicated to Professor Anderson, and a handsomely bound copy is to be found in the collection. As well as his magazine connections, Anderson held memberships in several learned societies: the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Chemical Society, the American Society of Biologists, and the Society of Experimental Biology and Medicine. He was also Vice President of the American Society of Biological Chemists, 1939-1940, and later President, 1941-1943.
Anderson served as a Captain in the Sanitary Corps of the United States Army, 1917-1919, and was then promoted to Major in the Army Reserve, in which he continued to serve for many years.
Rudolph John Anderson married Clara Tillinghast on June 3, 1920. He died on April 16, 1961.
For biographical details of a more personal nature please see box 1, folder 2, of the collection which contains a typescript of an autobiographical sketch entitled, "Adventures in the Education of Rudolph Anderson."
Scope and Contents
Writings and memorabilia of Rudolph John Anderson, professor of chemistry at Yale University, 1927-1948. The papers contain autobiographical memoirs, essays on the history of chemistry by Anderson and drafts of his book, The Chemistry of Lipoids..., published in 1938.
Chemistry -- History; Lipids; Science; Chemists; Anderson, Rudolph J. (Rudolph John), 1879-1961; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Chemistry
- Inventory, 1917-1962
  - Commissions in United Sates Army and United States Army Reserve, 1917-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Adventures in the Education of Rudolph Anderson, 1943," autobiographical sketch and notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Citation from Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research to Rudolph J. Anderson on his retirement from the Board of Scientific Advisors, 1952 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journal of Biological Chemistry, a history, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appointment and acceptance of Honorary Membership on Board of Scientific Advisors, Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research, 1957 February 27-1957 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Journal of Biological Chemistry, dedicated to Rudolph J. Anderson, 1958 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anderson, Rudolph John. "An Account of the Life and Work of Joseph Priestly", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anderson, Rudolph John. The Life of Berzelius, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anderson, Rudolph John. "The Scientific Congress in Scandinavia", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Edsall, John T., editor. Journal of Biological Chemistry report to American Society of Biological Chemists, 1961 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Edsall, John T. Letter of consolation to Mrs. Rudolph John Anderson, 1961 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vickery, Hubert Bradford, Rudolph John Anderson, A Biographical Memoir, National Academy of Sciences, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Chemistry of Lipoids of the Tubercle Bacteria and Certain Other Microorganisms, by Rudolph J. Anderson.
    - Introduction, notes, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Methods, Properties and Composition of Acid-fast Bacterial Phosphatides, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - The Acetone-soluble Fats of the Acid-fast Bacteria, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Acid-fast Bactrial Waxes, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Higher Alcohols in Acid-fast Bacteria, Pigments in Tubercle Bacilli, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Firmly Bound Lipoids of Tubercle Bacilli, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Are Sterols Metabolic Products of Acid-fast Bacteria?, The Lipoids of the Phytomonas Tumefaciens, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Lipoids of Lactobacillus Acidophilus, The Lipoids of Yeast, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bibliography, mss., [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Chemistry of Lipoids of the Tubercle Bacteria and Certain Other Microorganisms, by Rudolph J. Anderson
    - Typescript, pp. 1 -75, [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Typescript, pp. 76 -147, [pre 1955] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Certificate of membership in the Loyal Order of the Boar, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, 1929 July 18 (Box 2)
  - Photograph of a meeting of the Jane Coffin Childs Fund, 1941 September 12
  - Appointment as Captain in the Sanitary Corp, United States Army, 1917 November 8
  - Certificate of membership in the Yale Chapter of the Society of Sigma Xi, 1929 March 26
  - Certificate as Registered Pharmacist from the Board of the State of Louisiana, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1901 November 9
  - Certificate of membership in the Louisiana State Pharmaceutical Association, New Orleans, Louisiana, undated
  - Certificate of membership in The National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 1946 April 24
  - Degree of Graduate in Pharmacy, New Orleans College of Pharmacy, 1902 May 14
  - Bachelor of Science Degree, Tulane University of Louisiana, New Orleans, 1906 May 31
  - Degree of Doctor of Philosophy, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, 1919 June 23
  - Honorary Degree of Doctor of Medicine, University of Lund, Sweden (2 copies), 1947 May 31